<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Ask Nubia]]></title>
  <link href="http://asknubia.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://asknubia.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-27T20:42:10-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://asknubia.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nubia]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Toyota Mr2 2001 Engine Overhaul]]></title>
    <link href="http://asknubia.com/blog/2014/04/27/toyota-mr2-2001-engine-overhaul/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-27T19:59:35-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://asknubia.com/blog/2014/04/27/toyota-mr2-2001-engine-overhaul</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<table>
    <tr>
        <th style="text-align:center;" >
            BEFORE   ☹    
        </th>
        <th style="text-align:center;">     
            AFTER ☺
        </th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><img class="left" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_engine_1.png" width="320" height="320" title="image" alt="images"></td>
        <td><img class="right" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_engine_2.png" width="320" height="320" title="image" alt="images"></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><img class="left" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_engine_3.png" width="320" height="320" title="image" alt="images"></td>
        <td><img class="right" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_engine_4.png" width="320" height="320" title="image" alt="images"></td>
    </tr>
</table>


<!--more-->


<div>
    – Me: My car is without a heart 
</div>


<div>
    – Mechanic: Not only that, is so empty that it does not even have a soul!
</div>


<p><img class="center" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_no_engine.png" width="1000" height="268" title="image" alt="images"></p>

<div>
My spyder’s broken heart:
</div>


<p><img class="center" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_broken_heart.png" width="400" height="400" title="image" alt="images"></p>

<div>
The story started with a constant “click click” noise that bothered me even though the car performed ok.  With ok I mean reasonably, but not as I wish it to respond when increasing rpms.  Check engine light went on, oil was “disappearing” and the car warmed over the limit, but the temperature gauge was showing normal temperature.  I noticed the car was hotter than it should because the plastic covers for the shocks/struts next to the engine showed signs of molten plastic (plastics were deformed).
</div>




<div>&nbsp;</div>




<div>
    The mechanic had to open the engine and this is what we found:
</div>


<p><img class="left" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_unmounted_engine.png" width="320" height="320" title="image" alt="images">
<img class="right" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_unmounted_engine_2.png" width="320" height="320" title="image" alt="images"></p>

<div style="clear:both;"></div>




<div>
    One piston was hitting the walls of the cylinder and due to the conditions of the engine I decided to go for an overhaul.  I bought slightly bigger pistons (0.2) instead of the standards (0.18).  Worn signs can be observed in the old piston (right) in comparison to the new piston (left).
</div>


<p><img class="center" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_pistons.png" width="320" height="320" title="image" alt="images"></p>

<div>
    The engine block went to a machine shop to widen the cylinders’ diameter:
</div>


<p><img class="center" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_measuring_pistons.png" width="320" height="320" title="image" alt="images"></p>

<div>
    I also acquired new valves, gaskets, seals.  Especially important is the main oil seal (between the engine and the transmission) that once it goes bad, is expensive to replace due to labor that requires removing the engine to reach the cheap seal.  For that reason, even though mine looked ok, I decided to change the seal as a preventive service.  Plastic parts that degrade with time and leaks can happen.  From the materials point of view polymers are prone to degradation due to environmental aging.  Specifically humidity (hydrogen and oxygen) and UV light attack and break the polymer chains.  Plastics then lose their mechanical properties such as flexibility and elasticity.  Therefore, rubber seals might not be performing properly after few years (I’ll guess after 5-10 years depending on variables such as maintenance, weather, etc.).  Following is the kit I bought from ebay:
</div>




<div style="clear:both;">&nbsp;</div>


<p><img class="center" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_gasket_full_set.png" width="320" height="320" title="image" alt="images"></p>

<div>
    When putting the engine back together, the mechanic noticed that the intake manifold had something inside.  I was able to put get my hand inside and discovered that an internal piece was broken ☹  Therefore, I also bought a manifold out of a corolla from a junk yard.
</div>


<p><img class="center" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_manifold.png" width="320" height="320" title="image" alt="images"></p>

<div>
    Obviously spark plugs and ignition coils were changed for new DENSO ones.
</div>




<div style="clear:both;">&nbsp;</div>




<div>
    I thought of getting a new engine, but new was too expensive and the cheapest rebuilt was ~900dlls.  However, nothing would have been more satisfying than knowing step by step what is happening to the engine, the parts being replaced and the ones that stayed.
</div>


<p><img class="left" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_rebuilt_engine.png" width="320" height="320" title="image" alt="images">
<img class="right" src="http://asknubia.com/images/MR2/mr2_rebuilt_engine_2.png" width="320" height="320" title="image" alt="images"></p>

<div style="clear:both;">&nbsp;</div>




<div>
What still bothers me, is not knowing what was the root cause.  Why was the car overheating and not giving an alarm? Where was the oil in the intake manifold coming from? Was everything started from the broken part inside the manifold? How did it break??? Anyway, I’m very satisfied with the job done and every dollar spent was worth it.
</div>




<div>
After seeing the inside of this wonderful piece of engineering, I will spoil this car with deionized water and good quality oil. ☺
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
